Guide to the Margaret Lewis Livingston Papers, 1826-1842
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Margaret Lewis Livingston Papers
1826-1842
Livingston, Margaret Lewis, 1780-1860
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection contains 70 letters from Margaret Lewis Livingston to her second-eldest daughter, Gertrude "Gitty" Livingston Lowndes, which document her life as a wealthy wife and mother who split her time between New York City and her Hudson Valley estate in Staatsburgh, NY.
Biographical Note
Margaret (Lewis) Livingston (1780-1860) was born in Hyde Park, New York to Geraldine Livingston and Gen. Morgan Lewis. She married Maturin Livingston (1769-1847) around 1798 and the two had twelve children. Her second-eldest daughter, Gertrude "Gitty" Laura Livingston (1805-1883), married Rawlins Lowndes (1801-1877), a businessman from Charleston, South Carolina.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 70 letters from Margaret Lewis Livingston to her second-eldest daughter, Gertrude "Gitty" Livingston Lowndes, which document her life as a wealthy wife and mother who split her time between New York City and her Hudson Valley estate in Staatsburgh, NY.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Mother to Daughter: Letters of Margaret Lewis Livingston to her daughter, Gitty Livingston Lowndes by Mary Mistler (2020), is a transcribed and annotated collection of the letters in the Margaret Lewis Livingston Papers..
Subject Headings
Names:
Lowndes, Gertrude Livingston, 1805-1883; Livingston Family
Subjects:
Family--New York (State); Women--Social conditions
Places:
New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs
Document Types:
Correspondence
VCL Categories:
Family; Local History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, February 2026.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lydig Hoyt and Geraldine (Morgan) Thompson, great-great-grandchildren of Margaret Lewis Livingston, June 1951.
Container List
- List of letters from Margaret Lewis Livingston to Gertrude "Gitty" Livingston Lowndes, 1951 Jun (Folder 1)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1826 Dec - 1827 Feb; [3 letters] (Folder 2)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1834 Jan-Dec; [11 letters] (Folder 3)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1835 Jan; [2 letters] (Folder 4)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1837 Jan-Apr; [8 letters] (Folder 5)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1838 Jan-May; [14 letters] (Folder 6)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1838 Jun-Dec; [11 letters] (Folder 7)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1840 Jan-Dec; [11 letters] (Folder 8)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1841 Jan-Mar; [6 letters] (Folder 9)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1842 Dec 16; [1 letter] (Folder 10)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, undated; [3 letters] (Folder 11)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1826 Dec - 1837 May; [transcripts] (Folder 12)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1838 Jan-Dec; [transcripts] (Folder 13)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, 1840 Jan - 1842 Dec; [transcripts] (Folder 14)
- Letters from Margaret Livingston to Gertrude Lowndes, undated; [transcripts] (Folder 15)